

COMPUTER SCIENCE P.H.D CANDIDATE INTERESTED IN THE APPLICATION OF NLP METHODS IN COMPUTATIONAL SOCIAL SCIENCE

Unter Sachsenhausen 6-8, Cologne 50667, Germany

🛘 +49(221)47694-253 | 🗖 Indira.Sen@gesis,org | 🌴 https://indiiigo.github.io/ | 🗖 Indiiigo | 💆 @indiiigosky | Google Scholar

Research Interests

I'm interested in improving the measurement of political and prejudicial attitudes and behaviours from digital trace data using mixed-methods and natural language processing. My research aims to illuminate and characterize the potentials, pitfalls, and consequences of understanding such attitudes from unobtrusive digital traces.

Education

RWTH-Aachen and GESIS - Leibnitz Institute for Social Sciences

Cologne, Germany

P.H.D IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

ADVISOR: PROF. CLAUDIA WAGNER

Oct, 2018 - Oct, 2023 (exp)

Indraprastha Institute of Information Technology (IIIT-D)

New Delhi, India

M.S IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

Aug, 2015 - Dec, 2017

ADVISOR: PROF. PONNURANGAM KUMARAGURU (PK)

GPA: 8.67/10

Vellore Institute of Technology (VIT)

Vellore, India

B.S IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

Jul, 2010 - May, 2014

GPA: 9.1/10

Honors & Awards

2022	Research Award for Interdepartmental Collaboration , for interdisciplinary research collaborations	GESIS
2021 Summer Intern Award for Outstanding Innovation , Nokia Bell Labs	Common Intern Assend for Outstanding Innovation Nakis Dall Lake	Cambridge, UK /
	Summer Intern Award for Outstanding Innovation, Nokia Bell Labs	virtual
2021	Best Reviewer Award, ICWSM	virtual
2022		
2020	Travel Grant for attending EMNLP,	virtual
2020	Selected for SAGE Text-Mining Fellowship, SAGE, Ocean	London, UK (virtual)
2020	Selected as Facilitator for the Alan Turing Institute Data Study Group, 2 week hackathon where we	virtual
	worked with an Industry partner (CatsAI) to deploy explainable AI predictions	VIITUUI
2020	Travel Grant, For attending FAT* 2020	Barcelona, Spain
2019	Travel Grant , For attending Summer Institute in Computational Social Science (SICCS), Germany	Bamberg, Germany
2017	TA Excellence Award , Foundations of Computer Security	IIIT-Delhi, India
2017	Accepted to Summer@EPFL, One of 60 interns selected out of 2000 applications	EPFL, Switzerland
2015-	Dean's Merit List, For Academic Performance	IIIT-Delhi, India
2016		III I-Deli II, III ai a
2015	GATE Scholarship, Scholarship for Master's Studies	
2011-	Merit Scholarship, For Outstanding Academic Achievement	VIT, Vellore
2014	ment schotaiship, i or outstanding Academic Achievement	vii, vellore

Publications _____

Journal Articles

Depression at Work: Exploring Depression in Major US Companies from Online Reviews.

2022

Indira Sen, Daniele Quercia, Marios Constantinides, Matteo Montecchi, Licia Capra, Sanja Scepanovic, and Renzo Bianchi.

PROCEEDINGS OF THE ACM ON HUMAN-COMPUTER INTERACTION. TO BE PRESENTED AT THE 25TH ACM CONFERENCE ON COMPUTER-SUPPORTED COOPERATIVE WORK AND SOCIAL COMPUTING (CSCW)

DECEMBER 5, 2022 INDIRA SEN · CV

Visualizing Internal Sustainability Efforts in Big Companies. Chiara Ceccarini, Edyta Paulina Bogucka, Indira Sen, Marios Constantinides, Catia Prandi, and Daniele Quercia. IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications	2022
A Total Error Framework for Digital Traces of Human Behavior on Online Platforms Indira Sen, Fabian Floeck, Katrin Weller, Bernd Weiss, and Claudia Wagner. Public Opinion Quarterly	2021
Conference Articles	
Counterfactually Augmented Data and Unintended Bias: The Case of Sexism and Hate Speech Detection Indira Sen, Mattia Samory, Claudia Wagner and Isabelle Augenstein. Annual Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL)	2022 short paper
How Does Counterfactually Augmented Data Impact Models for Social Computing Constructs? Indira Sen, Mattia Samory, Fabian Floeck, Claudia Wagner and Isabelle Augenstein. Conference on Empirical Methods on Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)	2021
"Call me sexist, but": Revisiting Sexism Detection Using Psychological Scales and Adversarial Samples Mattia Samory, Indira Sen, Julian Kohne, Fabian Floeck, and Claudia Wagner. International Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM)	2021
On the Reliability and Validity of Detecting Approval of Political Actors in Tweets INDIRA SEN, FABIAN FLOECK, AND CLAUDIA WAGNER. CONFERENCE ON EMPIRICAL METHODS ON NATURAL LANGUAGE PROCESSING (EMNLP)	2020
Empowering First Responders through Automated Multimodal Content Moderation Divam Gupta, Indira Sen, Niharika Sachdeva, Ponnurangam Kumaraguru, Arun Balaji Buduru. IEEE International Conference on Cognitive Computing	2018 Best Paper Award
Worth its Weight in Likes: Towards Detecting Fake Likes on Instagram Indira Sen, Anupama Aggarwal, Shiven Mian, Siddharth Singh, Ponnurangam Kumaraguru, Anwitaman Datta. WebSci	2018 short paper
Workshop Articles	
What Human Rationales Tell us about Machine Explanations Indira Sen, Mattia Samory, Fabian Floeck, Claudia Wagner HCI+NLP Workshop, In Conjunction with EACL	2021
Measuring Public Opinion Online: Potentials and Pitfalls Indira Sen, Fabian Floeck, Claudia Wagner Women in Machine Learning (WiML), In conjunction with Neurips	2020 Poster
A Twitter Corpus for Hindi-English Code Mixed POS Tagging Kushagra Singh, Indira Sen, Ponnurangam Kumaraguru. Workshop on Natural Language Processing for Social Media (SocialNLP), In conjunction with ACL	2018 Data Paper
Language Identification and Named Entity Recognition in Hinglish Code Mixed Tweets Kushagra Singh, Indira Sen, Ponnurangam Kumaraguru. ACL Student Research Workshop	2018
Experience	
Snap Inc. RESEARCH INTERN, COMPUTATIONAL SOCIAL SCIENCE. ADVISOR: Dr. FRANCESCO BARBIERI Developing a Stakeholder-centred Framework for Multilingual Sensitive Content Detection	Santa Monica, USA Jul 2022 - Oct 2022
Nokia Bell Labs	Cambridge, UK (virtual)

Nokia Bell Labs

Cambridge, UK (virtual)

Intern at Social Dynamics Group. Advisor: Dr. Daniele Quercia

Jun 2021 - Aug 2021

• Understanding and Characterizing the sustainability efforts of companies from employee reviews.

- 0411 2021 7149 2021
- Developed mixed-method techniques for detecting employees' views on their employer's sustainability efforts using a deep-learning framework
- (SBERT)
- Results from the internship were published at CSCW'22 and IEEE Vis'22.

DECEMBER 5, 2022 INDIRA SEN · CV

SAGE Ocean London, UK (virtual)

SAGE OCEAN FELLOW. ADVISOR: DR. DANIELA DUCA

Oct 2020 - Dec 2020

- Contributing to a Text cleaning WebApp called Texti
- Working on NLP transformations in Python and documentation
- Results from the Fellowship are described here.

Computational Social Science Department, GESIS

DOCTORAL RESEARCHER. ADVISORS: PROF. CLAUDIA WAGNER, DR. KATRIN WELLER

Cologne, Germany Oct 2018 - Present

- · Identifying, Characterizing and Quantifying errors that occur when measuring attitudes from Digital Traces
- · Building robust and interpretable NLP methods for measuring social science phenomena
- Large scale Twitter data collection using Amazon Web Services (AWS) as a service for Social Scientists.

Precog Research Lab, IIIT Delhi

New Delhi, India

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE. ADVISORS: PROF. PONNURANGAM KUMARAGURU AND PROF. ARUN BALAJI BUDURU

Dec 2017 - Aug 2018

- · Landscaping the fake like marketplace on Instagram and characterizing fake likers, and their attack vectors.
- Detecting Multimodal Hatespeech on Social Media

CHILI Lab, École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Lausanne, Switzerland

Jun 2017– Aug 2017

SUMMER INTERN, ADVISOR: PROF. PIERRE DILLENBOURG

· Worked on inferring dependencies between EPFL courses based on Concept Mining and grading patterns

Nanyang Technological University

Singapore

Jan 2017- May 2017

RESEARCH ASSISTANT, ADVISOR: PROF. ANWITAMAN DUTTA

• Master's Thesis: Worked on detecting fake engagement on Instagram.

Teaching, Mentorship, and Academic Service

Translation Tutorial on the Total Error Paradigm for Social Inferences

Barcelona, Spain

FAT* 2020

Jan 2020

· Tutorial on diagnosing errors and biases in observational studies from digital traces

Introduction to Python and Data Science with Python

Cologne, Germany

University of Cologne

Oct, 2019

· Interactive, hands-on five-day lecture series for teaching introductory python concepts to social science doctoral candidates

Mentorship

SUPERVISED ON CO-SUPERVISED THESES

- Esi Doda (RWTH Aachen). Master's Thesis. Racial Disparities in Social Media Commentary about Football
- Vani Agarwal (IIIT-D). Master's Thesis. Improving Content Moderation through Co-Training
- Kushagra Singh (IIIT-D). Bachelor's Thesis. Information Extraction Tools for Code-Mixed Hindi-English Social Media Content

PC member

WEBCONF (2023), ICWSM (2021, 2022), ACL STUDENT RESEARCH WORKSHOP (2020, 2021, 2022), WIKIWORKSHOP (2022), HCI+NLP WORKSHOP (2022)

Reviewer

CSCW (2019, 2020), THEWEBCONF (2020, 2021), EMNLP (2020), ACL ROLLING REVIEW (2021, 2022), EPJ DATA SCIENCE (2022)

Skills

Programming: Python, R, Java, C++, C, MongoDB, SQL, Bash

Libraries/Tools: scikit-learn, pytorch, tensorflow, huggingface, keras, pandas, NLTK, NetworkX, Amazon Web Services, Amazon Mechanical Turk, Prolific, Qualtrics

DECEMBER 5, 2022 INDIRA SEN · CV